Guide to the Lawrence and Eleanor Mead Papers
Yale University Divinity School Library
Lawrence and Eleanor Mead Papers
1886-1994
1911-1939
RG 155
Yale University Divinity School Library
15
(29 boxes)
This collection documents the lives and work of Lawrence and Eleanor Mead. Lawrence Mead served in China under the YMCA from 1913-16, and 1919-1926. He taught English at Yenching University in Beijing from 1928-1939, and was unofficial "official" photographer for the University. Extensive correspondence and memorabilia shed light on the early lives and family interactions of the Meads. The photograph collection documenting Yenching University, and scenes and events in China is noteworthy.
Mead, Lawrence Myers, 1888-1954
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Mead family
Conditions Governing Access
Open to qualified researchers.
Biographical / Historical
Lawrence Mead was born in Plainfield, New Jersey on September 21, 1888. He attended The Hill School and graduated from Princeton University in 1911, with a BA, majoring in English. He entered Union Theological Seminary in 1911, but dropped out midyear with a severe infection. In 1912 he joined the International YMCA, and in 1913 was sent to China to become a teacher of English in the YMCA schools there, serving in Shanghai and Hangchow. In the summer of 1916 he returned to the US for additional graduate study. He married Eleanor Machado of Ottawa, Canada in 1917. During World War I, he enlisted in the US Army medical corps and was stationed at the base hospital at Camp Shelby, Miss.
Eleanor Machado was born in New York City in 1894 and spent her early years in Plainfield, New Jersey before her family moved to Ottawa in 1902. She entered Vassar College in 1913 and decided to become a missionary to China following attendance at conferences in Northfield and Silver Bay. Following her engagement to Lawrence Mead in the summer of 1916, she left Vassar to spend a year at home prior to their marriage and expected departure to China in 1917.
In the fall of 1919 Mead returned to Beijing, China as a member of Princeton-in-Peking and secretary of the Peking YMCA, together with his wife and first born child. In Beijing he taught English language, composition, and phonetics in the YMCA's Commercial School from 1920 until he came home furlough in 1926. During his two years in Canada and the US he received an MA in English from Columbia University, which included special training in Phonetics at London University in England.
In the summer of 1928 he returned to Beijing with his family (wife and now five children) to join the faculty of Yenching University, where he taught English, with the emphasis on spoken English. All entering Freshmen had to take his course in spoken English. While at Yenching, Mead became the unofficial "official" photographer for the University.
The Meads returned to the US in the summer of 1939. In 1940 Lawrence and Eleanor, became co-directors of the International Student Association of Greater Boston, located in Cambridge, MA. This organization, supported by the schools and colleges in the area, served the 2000 plus foreign students caught by World War II in the Boston area. Lawrence and Eleanor Mead retired to Cornwall, CT in 1952. Mead died in Cambridge, MA on September 28, 1954.
Frederica Rutherford Mead, sister of Lawrence Mead, was also a missionary in China, serving at Ginling College in Nanjing.
Scope and Contents
The Lawrence and Eleanor Mead papers shed light on three notable aspects of their lives. Letters and reports describe Lawrence Mead's work with the YMCA in China and at Yenching University. Further documentation of their time at Yenching University is available in the archives of the United Board for Christian Higher Education in Asia (YDSL RG11). Extensive family correspondence reveals the importance of the Meads' families in fostering their desire to do missionary service and in providing support throughout years of changing positions and furloughs. Lawrence Mead's avocation as an expert photographer is also well documented in the collection.
Series I, Family Correspondence, provides a very complete series of letters between Lawrence and Eleanor and their families, both before and during their time in China. The Meads came from privileged, educated families who provided strong support for their work. A sheet describing familial relationships is located in the first folder of this series.
The General Correspondence of Series II is less extensive but it provides a good chronological overview of the Meads' involvements from 1900 to 1950.
The Memorabilia and Artifacts of Series III include biographical documentation as well as collected materials related to Yenching University, music, missions, and Chinese life. Also of note are collected documents related to the evangelistic campaign for Chinese students led by John R. Mott and Sherwood Eddy in 1913.
Series IV, Photographs, contains primarily photos taken by Lawrence Mead in China. A large section relates to Yenching University but there are also many images of Chinese life, buildings, and scenery, including a notable sequence related to famine conditions in 1921.
Arrangement
Series I: Family Correspondence
Series II: General Correspondence
Series III: Memorabilia and Artifacts
Series IV: Photographs
Missions -- China; Young Men's Christian Associations -- China; Missionaries -- China; Mead, Lawrence Myers, 1888-1954; Yanjing da xue
- Family Correspondence, 1886-1902; Series I
  - Lawrence Myers Mead to family, 1896-1916
    - Lawrence Myers Mead (LMM) to Marie L. Mead (mother), 1896-1903 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - LMM from school, 1904-1906 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - LMM from school, 1906-1907 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - LMM from Princeton, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - LMM from Princeton & Europe, 1909-1912 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - LMM to Mrs. Lawrence Myers (grandmother), 1909 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - LMM from Seminary, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - LMM from Japan/China, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - LMM from Nanking, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - LMM from Hangchow, 1915-1916 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Lawrence Myers Mead from family, 1904-1917
    - Frederica R. Mead (sister), 1904-1912 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Margaret P. Mead (eldest sister), 1904-1909 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Marie Louise Mead (mother, née Myers), 1904 Sep (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Marie L. Mead, 1904 Oct (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Marie L. Mead, 1904 Nov-Dec (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Marie L. Mead, 1905 Jan (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Marie L. Mead, 1905 Feb-Dec (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Mrs. Lawrence Myers (grandmother, née Laetitia M Halsey), 1904-1908 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Marie L. Mead, 1906-1910 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Mead Family Correspondence on European Tour, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Marie L. Mead, 1915-1917 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Eleanor Machado Mead to family, 1905-1912
    - Eleanor Machado Mead (EMM) to Eleanor Whitman Machado (mother), 1905-1910 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - EMM to parents, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Eleanor Machado Mead from family, 1913-1917
    - Machado family, 1913-1914 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Machado family, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Eleanor Whitman Machado, 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - re. Eleanor M. Mead, 1886-1902
    - to Mr. & Mrs. Machado, miscellaneous, 1886-1902 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - to Mr. & Mrs. Machado, re. birth of Eleanor Machado, 1893-1894 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Lawrence M. & Eleanor M. Mead (LMM & EMM) to family
    - LMM & EMM to Marie L. Mead, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - LMM & EMM to Mead and Machado families, inc. photo books, from Peking, 1921-1922 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - LMM & EMM to Mead family, from Peking, 1924-1925 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - LMM & EMM to Machado family, from Peking, 1924-1925 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - LMM & EMM to Eleanor Whitman Machado, from New Jersey, 1926-1927 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - LMM & EMM to Mead family, inc. from Shanghai, Peking, 1926-1928 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - LMM & EMM to family, from Yenching University, Peking, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - LMM & EMM to family, from Yenching University, Peking, Ottawa, 1931-1934 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - LMM & EMM to family, from Yenching University, Peking, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - LMM & EMM to family, from en route to and in U.S., 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - LMM & EMM to family, from U.S., 1942-1943 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - LMM & EMM to family, no date (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Lawrence M. and Eleanor M. Mead from family
    - Eleanor Whitman Machado (Eleanor's mother), 1917-1918 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Eleanor Whitman Machado, 1927-1928 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Eleanor Whitman Machado, 1938-1942 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Eleanor Whitman Machado, 1943-1944 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Machado family, 1918-1919 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Machado family, 1924-1926 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Machado family, 1927-1928 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Machado family, 1933 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Machado family, 1934-1935 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Machado family, 1942-1946 (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Machado family, no date (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Marie L. Mead (mother), 1925 (Box 6, Folder 8)
    - Marie L. Mead (w/ enclosures), 1926 (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - Marie L. Mead, 1927 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Marie L. Mead, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Margaret P. Mead, 1925-1927 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Margaret P. Mead, 1928 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Mead family, 1916-1919 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Mead family, 1926-1929 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Mead family, 1933 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Mead family, 1934-1936 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Mead family, 1937 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Mead family, 1938 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Mead family, no date (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence re. death of Mrs. Frederick Goodhue Mead (née Marie Louise Myers), 1948 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Children of Lawrence M. and Eleanor M. Mead
    - From children at camp or school, 1926-1936 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - From Eleanor E. Mead (daughter) From LMM and EMM to children, 1934-1944 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Eleanor M. Mead to Lawrence M. Mead
    - EMM to LMM: from Peking, Ottawa, 1924-1926 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - EMM to LMM: from Ottawa, New Jersey (LMM in England), 1927 Jan-Jun (Box 9, Folder 2)
    - EMM to LMM: from New Jersey (LMM in New York), 1927 Oct - 1928 (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - EMM to LMM: from Peking, Peitaiho, Ottawa and Springfield, 1932-1933 (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - EMM to LMM: from Ottawa, Peking, Cambridge, Huntington, 1934-1943 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Lawrence M. Mead to Eleanor M. Mead
    - LMM to EMM: from London, 1926-1927 (Box 9, Folder 6)
    - LMM to EMM: from London, 1927 (Box 9, Folder 7)
    - LMM to EMM: from New Jersey, Ottawa, 1933 (Box 9, Folder 8)
    - LMM to EMM: from New Jersey, 1934 (Box 9, Folder 9)
    - LMM to EMM: from within U.S., 1939-1944 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Other family correspondence
    - Miscellaneous, incl. from Hill School to Mrs. Mead re. Lawrence, to Mrs. Mead from John R. Mott, 1905, 1917, 1928, no date (Box 9, Folder 11)
- General Correspondence, 1900-1987; Series II
  - To LMM from friends and regarding school matters, 1900-1911 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - To EMM from friends, 1902-1913 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - To EMM from friends, 1914 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - To/from LMM incl. re. YMCA work in China and the Eddy campaign in Hangchow, 1914-1915 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - To/from LMM incl. re. YMCA work, including from John R. Mott, Fletcher Brockman, 1915-1916 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - To EMM from friends, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Re. engagement of LMM and EMM, 1916 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Re. donation of tower clock to Hangchow YMCA, 1916-1922 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - To EMM from friends, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 9)
  - Re. wedding of LMM and EMM, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 10)
  - To LMM and EMM incl. from Walter Rauschenbusch and re. proposed return to China, 1917 (Box 10, Folder 11)
  - To EMM from friends, re. birth of Lawrence Myers Mead, Jr., 1918 (Box 10, Folder 12)
  - To/from LMM and EMM re. request for early discharge from Army duty, 1919 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - To/from LMM and EMM incl. from Dwight W. Edwards, Robert Gailey, circular letters of LMM, regarding YMCA work in Peking, 1919-1926 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - LMM with/regarding Chang Ssu-Chang, 1919-192 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - LMM from Ernest Joseph "Tad" Weekes, 1920-1928 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Re. purchase of house in Peitaiho resort and East Cliff Association, 1922-1935 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - LMM to/from Lin Jui, father of baby cared for by Meads, 1924-1928 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Re. Princeton-in-Peking, 1924-1925 (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - LMM to/from John Leighton Stuart, Presbyterian Foreign Mission Board and others re. Yenching University position, 1925-1928 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - LMM to/from T'sai Chih Yi, 1924-1935 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - LMM to/from Chinese colleagues and pupils, 1925-1935 (Box 11, Folder 10)
  - To EMM from friends, 1925-1927 (Box 11, Folder 11)
  - LMM to/from colleagues, friends, incl. circular letters from Sidney Gamble re. disruption in Peking, 1925-1927 (Box 11, Folder 12)
  - LMM to/from colleagues, friends, re. work and education, incl. circular letters re. work in Russia of Paul Anderson, 1927-1929 (Box 11, Folder 13)
  - To EMM from friends, 1928 (Box 12, Folder 1)
  - LMM from friends, colleagues re. education in NY, work at Yenching University, 1928-1930 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - To/from LMM and EMM, incl. re. conditions at North China American School, 1931-1933 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - To/from LMM and EMM, incl. re. work at Yenching University, 1935-1937 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - To LMM and EMM, incl. circular letters of missionary colleagues, 1942-1947 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Circular letter from LMM and EMM, 1950 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - From Janet Rhodes, 1983-1987 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - To EMM from friends, no date (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - To LMM, no date (Box 12, Folder 9)
- Memorabilia and Artifacts, 1905-1994; Series III
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains personal items as well as memorabilia from Yenching University, including articles, yearbooks and choral music scores, and collected Chinese artifacts, including clothing and accessories, ornamental items and figurines.
  - Personal Items
    - Scrapbook - LMM at The Hill School, 1905-1907 (Box OV1)
    - Canadian Conservatory of Music recital programs - Eleanor Machado, 1909 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Princeton memorabilia of LMM, incl. programs, notes, mission study information, 1910-1911 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Princeton Yearbook 1911 (Box OV1)
    - Harvard Class Day program, dance card, map, 1911 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Re. The Hill School, 1911 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Smith College memorabilia of Frederica Rutherford Mead, 1911 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Vassar Scrapbook - Eleanor Machado (Box OV2)
    - Biographical statements by LMM and EMM, LMM Alien Registration Certificate issued in UK, 1920, 1927 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - North China American School yearbook of LMM, Jr., clipping and program re. violin recitals, 1927, 1930, 1931 (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - The Hill School booklet of student essays, incl. by LMM, Jr., 1935 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - LMM attendance and grade record book, Yenching University; biographical tribute in Princeton-Yenching Gazette, 1938, 1939 (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Vassar Class of 1917 Reunions, 1942,1955 (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Eleanor Machado cards and memorabilia, lacing cards (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Mead family photo Christmas greeting booklet from Yenching, n.d. (Box 13, Folder 12)
    - Episcopal hymnal, leather case, notes (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Related to Yenching University
    - Publications, 1930-1935 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Publications, 1936-1948, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Yenchinian (yearbook), 1928-1929 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Music scores
    - China sings: folk-songs and fighting songs of China (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Choral anthology, compiled by Bliss Wiant, Yenching University, 1937 (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Requiem by Brahms, performed by Yenching Chorus, 1938 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Songs of Cathay, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Songs of Chinese children, 1936 (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Songs and games (manuscript typescript) (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Collected publications and documents
    - China - general, incl. "The War on China" pamphlet published by Communist Party of Great Britain, 1927-1936 (Box 14, Folder 10)
    - China - general, incl. description of conditions in Shanghai during Japanese invasion (1937), 1937-1939 (Box 14, Folder 11)
    - China - general, 1959-1965, n.d. (Box 14, Folder 12)
    - China - higher education, incl. re. Ginling College, University of Nanking, 1932-1953 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - China - mission work, Christianity, 1923-1951, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - China - Princeton-in-Peking, 1916-1936 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - China - programs for artistic events in Peking, 1923-1924, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - China - social welfare work, incl. two reports of Peking Association for the Relief of Destitute Native Women, 1924, 1937 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - China - YMCA: Evangelistic campaign for Chinese students led by John R. Mott and Sherwood Eddy, Eddy campaign in Hangchow; work in Peking, 1913-15, 1932, 1936, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Missions, not China, 1920-1939, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Wedding, birth announcements received from friends (Box 15, Folder 8)
    - Miscellanous pamphlet publications (Box 15, Folder 9)
    - Oversize publication "Rebirth of a Nation" edition of the China Press (Box OV7)
    - Yenching Alumni in the USA, 1984-1985 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Yenching Faculty Families newsletter, 1985-1994 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Artifacts
    - Chinese accessories: hats (straw, 2 cloth), shoes (man's woman's bound foot), 3 belt sashes, 1 belt with hook ornament (Box OV3)
    - Chinese ornamental items: brass wall hangings (Chinese characters), painted scroll, fan, beaded "wand", 3 lantern covers, bells, knob, doll in silk box (Box OV4)
    - Chinese clothing, n.d. (Box OV5)
    - Wooden figurines (set of 11), n.d. (Box OV6)
    - Handpainted cards, envelopes (Box 15, Folder 10)
    - Cards and sketches (Box 15, Folder 11)
    - Original and prints of lithograph of Dragon Screen (Box OV7)
- Photographs, 1920s-1930s; Series IV
  This series contains an extensive collection of photographs taken and collected by Lawrence Myers Mead.
  - Yenching University
    - Buildings and campus (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Buildings and campus (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Buildings, campus, student activities (Box OV8)
    - Album (Box OV12)
    - Faculty and student groups (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Student activities (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - China scenes
    - Miscellaneous, incl. Boxer Rebellion Memorial in Paotingfu (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Miscellaneous, incl. street scenes (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Miscellaneous, incl. temples, monasteries, Peking scenes, Hangchow, Shansi, Pei-Ta-Ho (Box OV9)
    - Miscellaneous landscapes, buildings, street scenes (Box OV10)
  - People
    - Chinese individuals and groups (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Chinese individuals and groups (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Groups and individuals, including YMCA groups (Box OV11)
    - Western missionaries (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Mead family reunion, 1982 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Mead family photos (Box OV8)
  - Topical
    - Famine relief, 1921 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Famine relief, 1921 (Box OV11)
    - World Student Christian Federation conference in Peking, 1922 (negatives) (Box 17, Folder 4)
    - WSCF 1922 conference photos in booklet (Box OV11)
    - Troops being trained in trades (Box 17, Folder 5)
    - Pottery, paintings, miscellaneous (Box 17, Folder 6)
    - Japan (Box 17, Folder 7)